yeah
okay
um so uh
prom 7 is due today as you probably know
from that uh two uh is um uh has just
been posted
um
now uh uh but at the end of the uh we
need to look at the processor right now
but today's lecture you should know how
to do common one and uh
in the new kitchen set is going to
concern technical field Theory actual
field Theory
um uh and uh you know I think at this
point I mean by next Tuesday you will
know that all the tools to do that but
you can also try to figure it out before
that by trying to generalize what we do
in a one-dimensional quantum mechanical
example which is actually not not so
hard to do
um and uh anyway the the new piece that
is a little bit more substantial than
the previous one and so the due date is
uh slightly over two weeks we do on the
Thursday
all right
um okay so now uh let's continue uh our
calculation of the uh euclidean uh two
point function in the uh
theory of the harmonic object there is
right remember this let's see uh the
graphics
there and we're looking at the graph
State uh expansion value of the product
will be two operators uh and this style
is the imaginary time
and as I also explained last time
emphasize this
um this is a probably only one
as a value only medium tau is a positive
um
uh now let me just comment on that uh
this particular expression as you saw
before
um and this paper right the right hand
side makes sense for power both positive
or negative but the left hand side only
makes sense is when power is
so if I were negative uh you're skipping
into something it's just we can do this
to uh with the water extension
and by exactly the same reasoning as how
we arrived
but anyway but for now let's just
discuss the okay it's part of it
let's be clear
all right and uh the way we're gonna
approach this the last time we studied
this with me on maybe we saw the
denominator
um we're interested in its dependence on
this uh coupling uh parameter G of the
unharmonic oscillator uh and we saw last
time that how we can calculate whatever
in a power series expansion in NG of
this uh now at every order as a result I
was actually Divergent due to this
integration time but we saw about the
integration of that was that would last
the correction the ground state energy
uh the power series engine
finite range of people in time after you
have done the computation both numerator
they take the limit that time range goes
Infinity they're supposed to arrive and
result which is a physically unambiguous
Equity value foreign
okay so the numerator uh
that's right uh according to the lottery
last time we're going to uh just expand
uh the action well each of the minus
action between an action we're going to
just expand this out in a power Series
in G and then we can write everything in
the numerator as uh they already know
how many positive Theory to the G Factor
zero
factorial
and we'll pull down this uh
pass some power and power of uh the
company term in the in the action which
is minus G over four factorial
it will be top Prime Q Prime of this e
to the force both into the N power and
this will be the equipment value taken
in
foreign
uh any questions about this
okay so um so let's look at what this uh
what this term actually looks like what
it is like again uh Builder by order uh
as uh
uh wow I mean we're not afraid of
calculating any kind of experience
in the Galaxy integral again the rule is
just with contracts okay computes
again compute really
um right so um uh so what what kind of
uh contractor do you typically have well
I'll just give you a random example for
instance uh if you have some
and
um
if you have some uh number of these
factors let's say uh material integral
Prime
right right and then you have a bunch of
attackers okay
um so here's one possible contraction so
one thing you can do is that uh you
might uh
you might contract uh let's say this
queue with a q in here so you have to
try this out I wanted to write it out
because
with that
not if you're there okay so now that
removes two of the cutesy here you still
have the two more cubes right so for
example you can try them with each other
you can do that or maybe this
awesome
okay so um now uh and we can represent
this diagrammatically just like people
the only modifications uh compared to
what we did last time but now we have
this extra cues
out here
so the the form of the graph
will look a little bit different so for
example let's just start this example in
this example uh just like last time
there's a cube report turn can be
represented by a Vertex with four lines
coming out each line represents a cube
uh so just to keep track of that let me
label the cues outside with some
uh just denoted by some red dots
all right so let's say you know this is
your Qs how
secure zero just to write this two
remains myself what is going on once you
get familiar with us you will not have
to write all that things but for now
let's let's write this and uh
represented by a line connecting this
red dots to the right leg and here you
have an internal pair of computers
inside the screen support which are kind
of one of these products so you can
disconnect these
uh now of course if you actually want to
calculate the whole thing uh there are
multiple different contractions looking
at the same answer right so you have to
be careful with them with sort of
factors uh we'll come to that in just a
moment
um so in this case uh if the contraction
is well this shape then this part of the
product will just give you the diagram
but we're not done
this this stuff right here but if this
was the case where you see here is that
the result it will be this times some
um let's say other uh graphs uh that are
disconnected from the this one have
drawn here how they're disconnected
and once I grab I mean the number that
represents which is given by the statue
of the interactions
um okay uh so uh it's not hard to see
how this will generalize so generally
um
uh generally
uh
the psalm
of all the of uh well uh uh let's say uh
this this uh extreme value at least in
fact some uh well uh factorized it is
that basically looks like the left-hand
side but with more company stuff in the
middle uh so we have some whatever it is
it will be connected
that's some kind of kinetic graph and uh
with uh these uh
purple legs coming out
and uh and um these uh uh queue now
thank you
so here's our question is the simplest
number example but we can we have you
can draw more graphs about Jordan in
just in just a moments and the question
as you might recall every graph are you
supposed to be keep in mind what is
represents is is a number this number is
calculated by uh
so associated with every vertex we have
a factor of minus two over four
factorial uh there's also integration
over Tau Prime and every purple line
give you a factor that is the this uh G
this uh
so for example in this case it's right
in here what are these purple line
represents this represents uh G uh how
uh Prime right so this particular point
then
represents
uh so so we're gonna have some status
connected uh and then at times uh the
stuff that is
disconnected graphs
um and this disconnect the graphs do not
have any
um
uh uh I do not have any uh assertions of
these rent thoughts the skew or 2000
user
I should say that uh aprara if you allow
arbitrary and interaction time it could
have been that I could also have a
situation where I have the skew outside
here and there was something with
nothing coming come on here and have
some ground over here connected to this
but this kind of diagram is not possible
in our current uh example uh because uh
zero you only have to have you must have
even number of cubes and in this case
every product will have an even number
of Cubes uh so so this will have a
problem review that that's not that's
just going to be zero there's no way
correction but in the homework problem
number two you'll see an example where
where that's not zero but I'm not going
to discuss that right now
all right so uh it's not hard to
accomage yourself that is this whole
thing is just going to be given by it's
in the background in this form where
this works factor is just the sum over
all the possible kinetic graphs uh
connecting to this uh red uh external
cubes uh and over here it's just a sum
of all the parts of disconnected group
graphs uh connecting or disconnect
graphs uh without I say this is
different from this stuff here without
any Q research
any questions so far
um uh but this stuff the sum of all this
stuff a welcome video already this is uh
this is
your last time
okay so uh but we're gonna divide it out
so you see that this is e here uh is
going to uh let's go to cancel against
over there
okay so so we're in luck uh for this
expensive value of a q q is a ground
state uh actually for the graph so even
the last time we studied laboriously
only some of these diagrams uh with no
external cues actually for this
particular problem we actually didn't
have to compute those they'll get
canceled between the numerator
uh but uh we're left with we're left
with this stuff which is a q here Q here
and the whole graph has to be connected
okay
um any question about this so far
foreign
that will be allowed
um so what we see here is that if we're
competing this quantity
um uh
you have to have zero
um so it will include is that we have an
expansion in powers of G
and uh by the way this of course is the
G to the first order there's G to the
zeroth order which is just the leading
term not just the QQ contraction in the
harmonic oxidative Theory so it starts
with the it starts with uh
um
so
this just represents uh uh the factor of
this uh G how zero
there's two point function in the um
uh this two point function in the um
uh later on I'm often going in the
context of discussing these graphs and
associated with this factor of this G
functions I'm also often going to refer
to the G as the propagation uh it's uh
slightly different from the definition
of property in the quantum mechanics
language but this will be the notion of
Provider later on when we discuss Theory
so so from now on I'm always going to
refer to this the G characters
associated with these with contractions
as the property
this
um
and uh uh so that's the first order term
so that's just
um
what we have is uh you tell zero uh so I
only have uh uh this is the diagram I'm
already drawn from here
and this wrap and as I said so up to
some overall uh Factor this is the
different ways to do the contraction uh
this is the only graph that appears so
for now uh even though earlier
um even though earlier when I droved it
through this graph I said every word
that comes with the factor of minus 0
over 4 factorial you have to keep in
mind that the different way to do the
contraction so uh when I write an
expression like this I don't want to
keep writing repeated in the graphs of
the same of the same uh type uh so I'm
just going to use this picture to
represent the sum of all possible weak
interactions so that that has to say
that okay well we'll see exactly what
the factor is in just a moment
um but as you can see there's really no
apart from permutation of these legs
there's no way to there's no other way
to contract
if you only have a once uh vertex
any questions so far
okay so so let's go on
um uh so then we need a two verses
like this
and
so you can have a conversion like this
repeat
uh anything else
what else can you draw well the rule is
that at the next one I said that you
know this is for the G there's no other
G squared or the D Squared have to have
two vertices but you're Contracting any
way uh you want so uh for example
you can have a Vertex here a Vertex here
and you connect them in this way
thank you so so that's that's one
possibility
uh any other possibilities does anyone
see any alternative
are we done at this order
so yeah there's one more there's this
right and uh and then we're done
actually so there's yourself that these
three are the only ones you can control
I just wonder there's really no more
literally this right I mean you know the
graph literally is a weak attraction
right there is a queue there's a cute
if you want to write in this in this
language but let me just write write it
down and let's take let's take this
example let's look at this guy so so
this guy would be
um
foreign
that
all right so so that's that's these two
external lines over here
and then there are three contractions
between these pair of vertices so you've
got three cubes left here so there's one
there's another one and another third
one
so the graph is an easy way to help you
organize uh what are the possible
contractions uh but you still have to do
a little bit of work to calculate how
many uh you know what are the coming
four factors that come in with each wrap
and uh we'll discussed that in a moment
any questions so far and of course the
series continues to hire you can see the
ground I got more and more complicated
um
all right so let's let's turn this uh
pictures into the formula
uh so
okay so um this first graph which is
just uh the probability itself between
the Q at times zero I won't keep writing
the Q I just indicate the the time to
remind myself the first thing is
supposed to be to put the represent from
the formula that is g Tau 0
um and just from now on but I'm just
going to write G like power one power
two and G of the different one we can
tell two because uh uh remember that
this is a time for special invariance so
it only depending on the difference
between Taiwan and Tau 221.
how
this one here's the propagated for this
this QQ two point function for the
harmonic oscillator with Omega sets of
one and uh that means one over two Omega
e to the minus Omega
now I said at the beginning that I have
assumed thousand department but uh if I
use the path label formula this would
also make sense for negative in fact let
me just a mistake that a bit more
explicitly uh from now on I'm going to
write if I write something like q0
um uh in the uh the editorial like let's
say in the um setting I'm gonna just
write this nearly useless if you note
um uh if this is a power that you put it
in time I'm going to use it to denote uh
this quantity
uh
for now on the negative positive or
assuming others the opposite ordering
which is well defined and we're now
negative and the way we encounter this
using the euclidean path integral uh the
Tactical formula is uniform in both
cases so so then I don't have to
distinguish and just use this this is
it works in both cases
all right
um
uh and uh you might recall that there's
a useful uh Fourier transformed
expression for this which will come up
which will be very convenient for us so
um so this geotel is useful to write
deploy a transform the version of it you
can write it as much as well as DK over
2 pi or minus infinity to Infinity okay
uh oh this one's going to be called a g
uh from now let me put a subscript zero
uh just to uh uh to to remind ourselves
that the G zero is this two point
correlator uh in the harmonic
oscillatory not to be confused with a
two-point coordinator in the anjaman
oscillator Theory right so this one now
right as a voltage G but anyway
just remind ourselves
okay
um so
um this guy has a four-year
representation
is the frequency uh well it's not a
group it's a pregnancy
but yeah uh it's uh everything is
real okay
uh and uh you might remember what this
particular case we discussed this
electric couple lectures ago so this was
one over K4 plus one before it was case
for plus Omega squared to not pay for
plus one because I said Omega aspect
it's more Simplicity of notation
all right
um
so that was the problem right there any
questions
okay so let's continue let's look at
this graph the second graph uh is Wonder
G so what is this
uh well uh so first of all uh
uh there is a Tau Prime
so so this vertex you want four cues
um at the time you put in time so there
was uh this integral in Tau Prime
um and uh we've got a doctor of uh minus
G over four factorial from vertex as
always
but on the right we have general account
right so it's a different community and
from here
we have a g
so top Prime and top parameter is zero
so let's do zero at the time yeah
separation too
okay so uh a single with contraction of
this shape will give us that number
uh but we have to remember that uh there
are several different ways to do this
contraction so let's let's remind
ourselves so we've got a q here and here
we go four cues
q and final activity
so how many ways do we have to contract
them
well that's a good run this first queue
with any one of these four I've got four
choices
there's a backgrounds right there's a
back and forth because we have four
choices so once I've made the choice I
can try this cube with one of these
three cubes I got three choices four
times three
and once I made these two choices I have
no more choice because I have two few
left I have to convertible and that's
not what it is contraction so that's it
so I have a factor of four times three
and that's it
so the result of this is uh equal to
minus Z over two uh what is the copy
done that
expression uh well let me just arrange
here so this whole thing is because
minus G over Z
um any questions so far
yes
uh so let me say this again so the first
few contract with one of these four
tubes I have four different choices once
I have made that choice if I could run
this cube with a remaining three I have
three choices
yeah
uh any other questions
it's very important to be able to cancel
this counting correct
uh it's also very important to get all
the science projects
correctly um
okay uh
you know in textbooks um in uh can be in
this kind of graphs uh often you will
find in textbooks we will talk about
symmetry factors but graph
um I would rather not to uh rather not
introduce that uh at least not for now
uh because I think it will just uh give
you because I'm actually confusion I
mean there's an easier way to to get
this kind of kind of a territory factors
not by laborers the accounting number of
ways to contracts but by studying the
order of the automobile group of the
graph but I don't want to Define that
because I think I've just introduced
some extra activities so let's just do
this the contraction which is really a
clear way look at least when the graph
is not very complicated it's very
complicated uh you might want to you
need to use web Theory but I'm not going
to need that in this course
uh
okay uh so uh of course this integral is
Elementary you can discover the integral
uh but I'm going to rewrite this
integral a little bit to make some of
the properties more manifest
okay so uh the first thing I'm gonna do
is to write every G 0 here using this
Fourier representation and this will
turn out to be always often very
convenient for calculating this let me
write you this I'll write this as uh so
minus G over two so I'm going to turn
every g into it
so this looks like maybe no cover time
for now but there will be a payoff later
uh so uh so each one of these so there's
a k the K Prime K double Prime so we'll
be right like that so d k so the first G
becomes DK over two PI right uh and then
there's the DK Prime over d p i uh uh
and uh uh uh
um
okay double Prime now these uh arguments
these time arguments we're going through
the exponential here so you see you have
this times e to the uh
e to the I uh okay uh Prime so this
comes with that guy that's for the
playoffs who was this perfect first
um and then we have a factor of feature
that let me just write this down in the
exponents we have personality so the
iPad coming some primers of that
um and then we have for the second
second propagator here we have e to the
i k Prime uh Tau Prime
all right
foreign
okay so first of all uh actually uh
look at this interval here of course
this K prime it doesn't appear in this
exponents
okay just duplicate Prime mineral
unfortunately chord just get back to
this that's kind of trivia this G zero
of zero is a number it's number is equal
to exactly one half so we actually
didn't have to write it out but I just
wanted right in this uniform way for
reference uh but the reason that you're
seeing it in a second but of course that
that one easy calculate
um and uh and then
we can uh interchange the order of pay
and tell Prime integral if we integrate
over top Prime first
um you see uh it's going to produce a uh
two times a Delta function uh right so
because the Tau Prime only appeared in
exploded integrals are over top one each
of the uh okay P to the i k Prime minus
K times Prime I'm just going to get the
two by times the Delta function the
Delta function will set K Prime to be
equal to K
so the result
so let me just uh continue to calculate
this so what we have is G number two
times uh responding one half this one
half this comes from just G zero of zero
so it is f that takes care of the K
prime a double primary table and then uh
we have the uh D Tau Prime integral E
power primary control uh is going to
give us
the e to the minus i k l prime plus
Prime is going to go too high Delta of K
minus 10 run
we do that we can then get rid of the K
Prime integral or nothing with physical
Decay over 2 pi and over here which is
how K Prime set to okay which until the
k
um
uh squared
uh let me just plug in the explicit
expression now so 1 over my K square
plus 1 squared
uh and then I'm still left with this is
um so uh so that's the result uh now I
mean of course you can try to uh
some more Premier function
um but as you will see for the reason
itself be kind of clear
um later today uh very often uh we don't
need to do that very often it's actually
more convenient to work with the whole
example of expression so so just look at
this 50 Grand here it's going to give us
all the information that we'll need
um uh but let me uh give you a kind of a
uh you know a diagrammatic shortcut or
whatever's answer in fact once you get
familiar with this it's not necessary to
write out all these steps you'll find
that it's always the same set of steps
it's very easy to arrive at this
expression without actually doing all
that
um so
uh what you can do is to look at this
graph
um so once before you transform you can
associate every leg every propagator
with this weight number okay later in
the field Theory context uh this K will
turn into something that would call the
momentum but for now this pay is just a
wave number that is the employee
transform of the variable the point
that's a little different parts of town
okay so so this you write hey here
associated with this this this problem
here here you have a k Prime
all right so remember the K was uh you
get my boyfriend will be the first
propagator that's this guy here K Prime
come from a boyfriend comes in the four
extension from the second propagator and
then and then we've got a k double Prime
um and the drop of the tower the Tau
Prime integral and the tile Prime is
theory
uh what do you tell a primary do we
produce some Delta function this Delta
function is set K to be equal to K Prime
uh actually if you think about think
about this whole thing uh generally well
that's how Prime integration does is
that it says the total number of this
wave number okay okay Prime whatever but
flow into this vertex that will add up
to zero so if you interpret this case
I'm kind of momentum it's not really the
momentum of this model but
later we'll have something with momentum
field Theory uh this just says that the
momentum is going to served at the right
expert so that the K is the flow in
equal to the K that flow out
uh that's it so you know if you if I get
confused about this rules just always go
back to the formula it's everything
would derived no I think
[Music]
um
so uh any questions about this
yes
so I have this factor and this factor
that identically give us one over K
square plus one squared
because remember the G was the one over
K square plus one
okay
all right so so the smarter this is
two-factor on the property and then I'm
just left with this exponential
everything else happens without friends
okay
oh yeah
uh the direction uh the direction is
always uh uh well uh well you see uh
there was an orientated to begin with
right this one's gonna tell mine is how
Prime this is how primary two so I just
do take a nice uh up to you right
because we're just putting label on the
graph it really is that's that's what it
is right so so you you pick one
conventional orientation but then it
takes this one scroll so let's say you
know our convention it's always going in
um so you know
and style prime before you transforming
this way we're gonna put the arrow
always going to come this Tau Primes
just pick One Direction
so evolving in yeah
yeah
okay any other questions
all right so
um
um so that's a that's an interesting
computation uh we're going to understand
the interpretation of this uh in a
moment uh now
um uh is more instructive for you to do
this more complicated yourself than in
the class and indeed uh these three
graphs are left uh in the home right so
that's the problem one problem a uh
it's a really not that difficult uh but
you know these are
um it might look difficult it might look
complicated anyway first time you see it
but once you play with this doesn't work
it's really going to be quite
straightforward and it's important to
get familiar with this uh with this kind
of manipulation because uh you know
we're going to encounter a lot more
sophisticated version of this in the
field Theory where we have to worry
about you know the regularization some
of these kind of terms of all that if
you're not familiar with the basics okay
the massive you can do is
foreign
uh okay
so uh so okay so that will be uh
um but uh but what is the general
structure so let's get to some idea of
the of the general structure
whether you you get by signing up this
kind of graphs so as we said
um the full uh result at least to all
other in this copy Factor G is supposed
to be calculated by uh the sum over
all the connectors
graphs like this
you know harmonic acid in the theory
um so let's think about let's try to
organize it just a little bit even
though the sum of all graphs will be
fairly complicated as you might imagine
um uh there's a there's a useful way to
to organize this so for example we
always start with the problem
you know
um and um
uh and it's possible that uh uh it's
possible that uh this this wrap uh well
connected uh might separates into into
the district
that uh you know uh it might be like
pumped up here sometimes yeah but
there's a line
um now I'm going to convince you in a
moment that you can't indeed organize it
this way uh in terms of new more
Elementary building blocks
okay so and uh and so forth
um uh so I'm really declare that
actually you can think about all they're
going to connect graph like this in the
following way there's something that I
did not by one Pi this will refers to
the shorthand for one particle
irreducible
um so what does ybi stands for what
stands for is that this is a graph
but my definition is defined to be a
graph that cannot
be
disconnected
um
[Music]
okay so so for example uh so for example
uh if you look at this graph that we
have already seen
I'm just looking at the the thing in the
middle so not counting the external legs
so over here the only thing I could cut
is with that but if I cut it uh it's
still kind of still connected
or if you look at something like this
because
any one of these internal legs or the
propagators uh in this stuff is still
connected so that let me buy one
particle are used
a graph like this of course uh will not
be one part of original because if I cut
this this one separate into two parts
but the claim is that you know
uh I can photographs by this by taking
all the possible one particularly
reducible graph one of the eye graphs
over there one paragraph over here they
have one line coming out and uh and I
form a graph like this and then the next
I can have detail uh and yeah I uh
one of the eye and it ends another Cube
and and so on so forth you can imagine
um uh what is that so every time here
when I draw the 1pi I mean the sum of
all the possible one particular
irreducible graphs that connect to these
two external points
uh is are people is everyone convinced
that all the kinetic graphs have been
represented in this way no objection to
this formula
yes
why yeah I guess uh wow so far uh no
reason uh so far that's to say that
again I can't dig them both into a
simpler transitions uh but uh but that's
the reason you'll become clear in just a
moment so these things will have
important interpretation
um but for now this is something I can
do with the identity that's true yes
when I come over like this when I came
to draft speed but
the second the first second order one we
just got them right now I'm sorry which
one are you referring to the first one
the first one yeah that's right this one
is not ypi right because this one will
fall into this exactly
[Music]
why is that
um it's because uh well let me uh
all right
so
um if you calculate the Fourier
transformed version of that uh two point
function
um all right so according to our
rule of the flow of this wave number
okay
momentum right it sounds like this
all right so whatever that is doing
inside uh there's some code that goes in
here that's the same thing out this is
going to blow out here okay
um so
um and uh so the result of a a graph
like this if you actually use the rules
that we have at this y to calculate uh
we're just going to get the product a
bunch of identical
identical factors Each of which is going
to be a function of K they're all the
same function
all right in fact
um so for example
uh this this first guy here
this one let me this one as we know is
the G zero this was the harmonic
propagator
uh now the next one is this guy
well
uh whatever it is you know there's going
to be some um
[Music]
so whatever it is uh it's gonna come
with a factor of G zero here and the
factor of G zero here
um well that's really imagine the
providers and
um well if I read this in in terms of
the Junior's house I'm not taking
particular product because
but if I look at the what extent from
the whole thing then uh organization I
just have 0 because okay yeah I just
have an apartment user available
through this this rack for the reason we
explained earlier when that's the result
of integrating out all these Primes
universities inside this the scrap
um so the result of this graph is just
going to be a g is going to be General
tilde K uh time well squared times some
other function uh okay let me call it a
sigma okay the sigma K is the result of
calculating uh the uh you know the the
information over the internal wave
number okay Prime whatever you have uh
associated with all the graphs like
something together okay whatever it is
it's going to give it a stop option okay
but if you know that by Sigma okay
um but if you know what Sigma K is you
will know the next one
this one
uh the
all right this one the four examples
okay uh
you have two factors
and from this and so on so forth so just
add every every time you add another 1pi
you're gonna you're gonna get another
Factor
together another packet of Sigma okay
so the whole thing
so the whole thing would be uh
uh so uh
this thing which is our let me give this
name let me call this the bolt space g
uh
this was uh this is
how
zero it's very evaluated I defined right
inside of the word uh in the I'm
harmonic Oscar Theory at least return G
um so this is supposed to be so what we
learned now is that you can show your
reputation you know there's the detail
number two Pi is row e to the i k Tau
uh of the sum of all these things
and so forth and the sulfate in the
geometric Series so this is
n from zero to Infinity okay
uh the same in the pay
with n power
with no extra commentary patterns
professional just one uh and N is the
number of 1pi bubbles appearing here yes
why why is
that down there the bottom right into
graphs yes so in that case the 1pi
bubble represent the sum of these two so
when I have to write about the eye I
mean the sum of all one bis with these
two legs coming out
good
uh any other questions
all right uh so uh now we might as well
do the sum because that's very easy to
do you want to know how to do this
geometric series
so the result
is um
so the result is that both page G of tau
is integral Decay over 2 pi e to the I
can tell
okay
saying okay
right so we let that be right in that
way but you remember so recall that uh
two zero code okay for us is the one
over x squared plus one so you can
describe this as
this whole thing as an integral being
paid upwards of Pi e to the i k Tau uh
e to that I K Tau over
all right
um
and uh just to uh remind you uh once
again hey how would you actually
calculate my pay so
um
so here Sigma k
um is uh conducted by the one pi
uh graphs the sum over one over one all
the one there graphs let me say that uh
you know
uh
without
including without the external
uh
obviously though of course you have to
draw the line here uh but uh we actually
accomplished Sigma K we don't take an
account of this GTO the zero on the
outside right that's that's how we
Define it
without wisdom come so this this
external probability that is
okay so
um uh usually uh we often refer to this
as a amputated graph in the sense that
um
uh in the sense that this external legs
are removed
uh and if you uh in our Theory
write it out as an expansion you see
it's just the sum of this Plus
the next order we have this and uh and
this
um
again without external X right uh and
and then energy equals
it'll be sum of all of that
but but they don't they don't repeat so
you like because
the this diagram for example we'll just
do already so this is not here
that we want
all right
uh any questions so far
yes the person one was like two with
like if with some with the middle ground
do I have to do like cases where like
the first Tower
yeah yeah I mean you know it all graphs
uh as long as my congratulations
we have this and Minnie Mouse I don't
know the cactus
so I would consider like cases of like
where like um
like the base vertex is which of the
towel because we have like all prime
double Prime uh doesn't work every every
vertex will come with an independent
power parameter uh and they use the if
you use the uh display type of
representation you don't need to
integrate of the entire access anymore
but you have a conservation of this case
and enemy vertex foreign
um
uh so uh the first web we have already
calculated this was this minus G over
two times four remember uh we are
stripping off the problem right so so
for the sigma K actually it's just the
pre-pack this man the jewel report
that's the first
so this this graph just gave us this
number minus 0.
uh and the sum of these two graphs uh
you can calculate so uh so this was
times
okay so your homework exercise the part
of it is to to recover your systems
um all right
um so
um uh so let's uh uh so that was
concludes about uh this analysis uh what
have we learned so far uh
we have learned that the we're outside
two-point version function if you had Q
hat in the AHA Market
or Theory
right so this one all right bone space g
which was integral okay uh okay
okay
is of the form uh one over
K squared plus 1 minus Sigma K and it
will be uh
so minus let's say plus G over four
minus G squared over eight uh
plus nine uh plus uh calculating
um now uh why did I
um
um okay you see uh so why did I sum up
the geometric series I could have said
that you know I'm just gonna take this
whole thing and expand to this whole
expression expand in our G and start at
G Square Order uh now I found the parts
over summation right you see what I'm
calculating here uh even though I'm only
I've only done a calculation after G
squared order explicitly you want to do
this this part is let's see
um and uh but it actually secretly
contains
because
experience in series right
you don't have any more diagrams for
example
um diagrams like uh like
like this one
this diagram will be happening in Canada
already
not everything but uh it's a lot more
than what you would just have a second
one
okay so that's Point number one but
that's uh you know you're gonna say that
well why is that special
diagrams so what's the big deal that you
have can't calculated some but not not
the rest
um uh well okay so here's the point uh
what is the uh
um but let's say if you're interested in
studying the energy Spectrum or the and
harmonic acid the most basic observable
in quantum mechanics
um as we said before you can extract
that information from
um
uh from this two-point variant function
so let me remind you that uh Spectrum
Edition
several times what does it look like
um
so we know
uh for instance that
um
this guy here you have how
things really value this is seriously
that's the same as that's for uh that's
how greater than zero right uh this one
as we have to before can be decomposed
by inserting a basis of energy eigen
space normalized
um so that this looks like uh and value
Q sorry and measurement of two and zero
zero there's another one with a zero and
switch a q is a few thyroid permission
so this is the amount squared a lot of
times e to the minus E N minus e0
the information of the difference
between the excited States and the
ground state
we said this before
so that's the same function where
calculator
uh now so how would you read up
information about the energy spectrum of
your polynomial system from that
employee representation at the first
look this is pretty weird
uh because uh
as you see
uh
as function now or okay there there we
have some function Tau in the smaller
transform right but what function of
cloud do we have what have each of the
ik power K the real by definition this
integration are very okay
the the exponent here an exponent here
are totally different
okay
uh so how can that be
right the time is in different function
well first of all there's no
contradiction because nobody says that
uh you know uh they cannot be too into
or some representation of the same
function one over integrated or some
over real exponents the other one
integrated over imaginary exponents so
there's a contradiction we might have
seen the example of this an example we
have seen before
was that uh in fact I wrote this just uh
earlier today
all right
um as you might recall there was an
example we saw that integral Decay we're
going to Pi of each of that I came down
over the K square plus one was equal to
one half e to the minus power of the
value so if you take account to be
positive it's important is this right so
you see here
you have e to the minus Tau the left
hand side you have e to the ik power
only star 99 exponents but they're equal
there's no problem
but in general how how did you how do
you read off you could have expression
on 11th time how would you know uh you
know what kind of exponent can appear
okay well we discuss this rule I think
the second lecture
uh well a simple way single trick to do
that you use a controller right so we
saw that as you recall from our uh in
the second lecture the left hand side if
you think of this as a contour edible on
complex territory
as a pair of bows
one above the real axis one below the
real axis right higher the minus Pi or
the okay okay
and uh if power is greater than zero so
this whole thing is explanatory
suppressed at large uh positive
imaginary k
then you can close the Contour
on the upper half plane and represent
this accountable integral and you treat
the Contour and pick up the revenue uh
and I can do this
so uh the lesson of that simple example
was just that if you have this integrand
or this shape
if it's sufficiently suppressed at the
Infinity on the upper half plane let's
say and you have some hose uh then uh
the results in the country is equal I'm
just gonna every call is gonna give a
residue that looks like each of the some
number of times down
in this case it is
okay so uh now we can play the same game
with that
in fact uh it does not require uh
to this so what is it what do we expect
um
yeah this is
the version of that right so we're just
correcting this
is
one of our character plus one uh but now
has something much more complicated
um
but whatever it is
uh we expect since the system are
probably about is just one mechanics in
the particle one being in the potential
the bouncing around like this right
energy levels
yes so whatever it is whatever the GK
data is you're invited the summer row
very complicated graphs we could do a
few of them but whatever it is the whole
thing has to integrate into something of
attackers
um so uh so how could that happen well
uh you know what was it the only way
that this can happen is if
um
this uh the complex
okay
um we're gonna find is that so we'll
have this real integration Contour
and that's how we Define that integral
this way thanks one but
it must be
that so I'm gonna be agnostic
about what having the law happens this I
don't really care I mean the focus on
the other half planes because that's
relevant for for the combination yeah it
should be positive okay we can discuss
what happened Lord helpline but that's
not relevant for our current newspaper
so
um whether it is I must have some
sequence of posts uh this post must be
uh as a positive imaginary values of uh
okay interesting because only if the
codes are as positive Imagine by the
okay when I calculate the residue I'll
get e to the minus something times the
power the something is about the real
number
just like in this example
uh and in fact if I find a oh study off
that foreign
so then it's not surprising that this
particular pay has to be someone
complicated because they have to have
infinite number folks every poem
correspond to a possible and the dragon
states that has measure overlapped with
two hands yes
whatever the case
that's correct because in that case as
we have as I have comment down before
nothing more
that's actually indicate the harmonic
and you know it could happen written as
a very annoying operator
but that's not true
this will have overlap actually uh
because there was a parody symmetry
with that first excited third excited so
all the odds
foreign
that's also why it was uh kind of useful
to sum up the geometric series because
we're going to be asking okay the
question of where are the posts is ask
where the denominator vanishes all right
um if you if I did some of the geometry
series you will never find the post at
least if you're translating the
perturbation here during the final order
you'll never find folks because uh you
will you will in fact you have made a
mistake you had said you would have
thought that maybe the polls are still
at uh you know okay he goes bye because
you have one over K square plus one well
the thing is that you have you have a
whole series when you restart the series
you find the post position would have
been shifted
is our easy to deduce because you know
in the case of the harmonial center uh
you see one pole for the reason we just
said
um and that one will probably get
stripped a little bit as you pronounce a
little bit interaction well where is it
shifted to well it's not hard to receive
from that formula right so
um so uh uh
uh
uh at uh let's say uh okay it was so
okay hi
uh this corresponds to the person
uh excited state
excited there's faith
of the uh anthemum
um
and uh you can just see uh
what is the value so you know you can uh
you can uh so so what is the value uh
close to it goes to I uh which is
another advantages and uh but okay you
have to have a little calculation
because well actually it's not it's not
so hard to do because uh
um you might worry about this um
if you expand around K close to I the
correction must be opposite t uh so any
correction to this away from K plus I
would be higher order
G and so to G Square Order you don't
have to worry too much about that and
the result you'll find this corresponds
to the call
is
trying to figure square root and G over
H minus G squared over 32 Plus
so this correspond to uh in other words
the Gap e y minus e0
all right so so from this we conclude
that um
the result of this little calculation uh
will tell you about other things this
can take more information than this
energy Spectrum but in particular you
can learn about energy Spectrum you
learned that the gap between the first
excited state and the graph State I had
an expansion uh one for the harmonic
operator and then the Restoration in G
and b square foot
okay
uh and let it reminds you for doing
nothing but you know a good old you know
undergraded quantity campus so far so
you could have replayed reproduced this
results from coming per Direction here
in second order or if you want you can
just forgive a plug-in value of G that g
equals 0.1 and solve the shortening
equation numerical you must recover the
answer is consistent with this so uh you
know if you do anything about all this
path in the world magic uh you can
always check the answer using other
methods
number two will be vastly more
convenience for filter generation yes is
the scariest trixology
uh the the series in the powers of g no
it does not converge
um it does not converge uh for
there's a very simple intuitive reason
why they converge uh it's just that well
it's not the readers written name but
they gave us why you may not converge uh
you know if it converts it'll be
something function for small G
um if we converted to black or answer uh
but uh which will behave so it wouldn't
be similarly for g75 or something but
you know for that one we have a system
if you have a g time to keep on the
fourth potential with the sign language
from below so something will not become
catastrophic right
Progressive so so that's the hint why
you don't actually expect this thing to
converge
um that does not mean this proximation
doesn't do anything in fact there's a um
what you can still understand that the
proclamation is still a good
approximately after some people order uh
that is just compatible they provide
that to you small
um but that is the discussion that I
will not get into
so
um any other questions
okay so um
uh that's all I'm going to say about
harmonic uh
I'm going to uh one more example notice
I don't have much time so I'm just gonna
tell you what the example is uh and
we'll discuss it uh uh analysis next
time which should not take more than
half a lecture and that will actually
we'll be doing generally good theory
um so uh but the reason I want to
explain the third example is uh have to
do with uh
something that will show up over and
over again in in the continuing field
Theory right so
um so thanks for example we'll discuss
is again following mechanics
yes what can I do with one mechanics
with Vladimir Freedom well uh let's
start with uh let's go to the ground
here for the harmony officer and I'm
gonna add a interaction term okay so
previously added and keep the four uh
now let me consider something different
I'm going to add a term like this uh
minus some coefficient it's still called
it g because she had nothing to do with
our OG this is a new Theory the new
model right uh it's not important to you
I encourage you over eight uh Q squared
uh Q dots
okay
all right
um I'm allowed to do this you know
lagrangea mechanics right because
they're like only mechanics actually uh
normally says
the queue will could be any generalized
coordinates I'm allowed to redefine
non-linearity what my general coordinate
is and the all the ground equation the
classroom mechanics will be completely
boiled right so you're allowed to use
whatever quantity you want the franchise
your mechanical system for example uh
for the rigid three-dimensional rigid
body you can use some other coordinates
doesn't care there's all equipment yes
what happens is
uh uh well uh I'm gonna say this with a
sign of genes ah and also I'm going to
treat it for terminally so so let's not
worry about
uh
uh okay
um and uh so um so you know in general
we have a connection like Q Power Square
if you make a relational variable not
linearly your produce a parents just
like that uh
anyway
um so let's look at the ham intelligence
what's the time I'm telling you well I
can write a hand in terms
this is a step in the learner transform
uh as uh somebody to do this you can do
that
um one minus G over four
to this way
um and so by definition
is Q dot P minus l
but subject to a replacement of Q naught
replaced by the expression in terms of
the T right so
imagine that
um and if you're just plug in calculate
and express the result in terms of a b P
what you find is one half y minus G over
four Q squared
inverse these words plus one half this
one oh I said how many other correct it
in some way but you're correcting the
kinetic term
all right
um so this is
um so uh next time we'll discuss the
quantum version of this now you already
see it is
going to be some celebrity
perspective uh you're gonna have to
worry about ordering of these and q's
so there's some pleasure ambiguity we
mentioned this before so so
um and not surprisingly you will imagine
that end up happening on LeBron James
when you contact you to the passenger
World there'll also be some kind of
ambiguity
uh we'll see what happens next time is
that uh if you're not evenly just
calculated this kind of climate diagrams
as we did today for these kind of
correlative functions uh you'll find
some divergences you'll find that this
uh okay integral will give you different
cities
um but you know the time you know it's
perfectly good times
yeah so
um
um so so there's a bodycon mechanical
system
um uh but but you will find some
divergences in this video diagrams
uh and we'll see that how that will be
resolved uh the resolution will have to
be that you have to carefully regularize
the pattern well you have to cut off the
range of integration in the momentum
we've had to add counter terms all of
that will be uh familiar and see it over
and over again is build theories uh but
in this case
you know you know that it's a good
mechanical hamiltonian there cannot be
anything wrong with it provided right on
Hamilton yeah so there has to be
sensible answer right so so you know
even though this is lagrangian having to
grow you run into some naive learning
some infinities you know they're having
result in some way I will learn how that
will result
I don't know
um